<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Utilities on The Patch Panel</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/utilities/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Utilities on The Patch Panel</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 14:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/utilities/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>How to Align Data Science with Business Strategy (And Stop Being a Science Project Team)</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/businessstrategy/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 14:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/businessstrategy/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://192.168.100.63:1313/img/head/business.png" alt="Featured image of post How to Align Data Science with Business Strategy (And Stop Being a Science Project Team)" /&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ai-summary&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ai-summary&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI Summary
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most data science teams solve technically interesting problems that create zero business value because they never question whether the problem is worth solving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;True transformation happens when data scientists embed with business consumers to understand their actual workflows, constraints, and decision-making processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success comes from ruthless focus on extracting value, not from building impressive models that sit unused&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The gap between data science potential and business reality stems from misaligned incentives, not technical limitations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stop-being-the-cool-data-team-nobody-actually-uses&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#stop-being-the-cool-data-team-nobody-actually-uses&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Stop Being the &amp;ldquo;Cool Data Team&amp;rdquo; Nobody Actually Uses
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The request seemed straightforward enough: predict which pole-top transformers will fail before they blow up. Classic predictive maintenance. Sexy AI problem. The kind of project that gets executives nodding approvingly in steering committee meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team dove in with enthusiasm. Weather data, load patterns, maintenance histories, asset ages. We built a sophisticated model that could predict transformer failures with decent accuracy. Months of work, impressive technical depth, ready for production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I started questioning the fundamental premise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back to the engineer who requested it. &amp;ldquo;Walk me through what happens when we get these predictions. What changes in your workflow?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer was illuminating: &amp;ldquo;Well, we run pole-top transformers to failure. When they blow, it usually doesn&amp;rsquo;t affect many customers. They&amp;rsquo;re quick, easy, and cheap to replace.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What changes?&lt;/em&gt; Nothing. Absolutely nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Factor in false positives - the cost of unnecessarily replacing functioning equipment - and our sophisticated prediction model was worse than useless. It was actively destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn&amp;rsquo;t a failure of data science. This was a failure of alignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-uncomfortable-truth-about-most-data-science-work&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-uncomfortable-truth-about-most-data-science-work&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Uncomfortable Truth About Most Data Science Work
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;After wrestling with this problem across multiple projects, a pattern emerged. The majority of data science initiatives in large organizations are solutions in search of problems. They&amp;rsquo;re technically impressive, methodologically sound, and completely divorced from business reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional wisdom about data science teams is starting to show its cracks. Companies pour millions into analytics capabilities, hire brilliant technical talent, and wonder why their ROI remains stubbornly elusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not because the math is wrong. It&amp;rsquo;s because nobody asked the right business questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-actually-drives-business-value&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-actually-drives-business-value&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Actually Drives Business Value
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pivot point where the whole situation shifts is when data scientists stop thinking like researchers and start thinking like business partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t just theory; this is from the front lines of enterprise data science in a heavily regulated utility environment. The transformation didn&amp;rsquo;t come from better algorithms or bigger compute budgets. It came from fundamentally changing how we approached problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embed with Your Consumers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most impactful change we made was getting our data scientists out of their offices and into the field with the people who would actually use our work. Not occasional check-ins or requirements meetings. Deep embedding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our analysts started spending time with vegetation managers, understanding their seasonal planning cycles and budget constraints. They sat with customer service representatives during storm events, watching how decisions get made under pressure. They attended safety briefings with field crews to understand operational realities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This immersion revealed something critical: the gap between what we thought people needed and what they actually needed was enormous. More importantly, it built the trust required for real adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question Every Problem Statement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we build anything now, we run through a brutal filter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who makes decisions based on this analysis?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do they use for those decisions today?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will our work integrate into their existing workflow?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What specific action changes if our predictions are accurate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the cost of being wrong?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can&amp;rsquo;t answer these questions clearly, the project dies. No exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach challenges some long-held industry assumptions about the value of data-driven insights. Insights without decision changes are expensive trivia. We&amp;rsquo;re not in the business of producing interesting trivia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design for Operations, Not Presentations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subtle detail that changes the entire equation is this: most data science work is designed to impress stakeholders, not to integrate with operational systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Models that require manual interpretation don&amp;rsquo;t scale. Dashboards that need explanation don&amp;rsquo;t get used. Recommendations that don&amp;rsquo;t fit into existing approval processes get ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started designing everything with operational constraints as primary requirements. Regulatory compliance, union agreements, procurement cycles - these aren&amp;rsquo;t afterthoughts. They&amp;rsquo;re the foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-portfolio-reality-check&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-portfolio-reality-check&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Portfolio Reality Check
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not all problems are worth solving, even if they&amp;rsquo;re technically solvable. This realization introduces a new layer of complexity that most data science teams ignore: resource allocation based on business impact rather than technical interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We implemented a ruthless triage system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High-Impact, Clear ROI Projects&lt;/strong&gt; get the majority of our resources. These are problems where the business case is obvious, the decision-makers are identified, and the integration path is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capability-Building Initiatives&lt;/strong&gt; get limited investment. These might not have immediate payoff but build technical or organizational capabilities we&amp;rsquo;ll need for future high-impact work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pure Exploration&lt;/strong&gt; gets minimal resources. Yes, we still do some blue-sky thinking, but it&amp;rsquo;s a small percentage of our portfolio and it&amp;rsquo;s time-boxed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core principle to carry forward is this: every project must pass the &amp;ldquo;so what?&amp;rdquo; test. If you can&amp;rsquo;t explain why the business should care in terms they understand, you&amp;rsquo;re probably solving the wrong problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;navigating-the-cultural-transformation&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#navigating-the-cultural-transformation&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Navigating the Cultural Transformation
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This approach renders the old way of doing data science obsolete. Some team members struggle with the shift from academic-style research to business-focused problem-solving. That&amp;rsquo;s predictable and manageable with the right framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Data Scientists:&lt;/strong&gt; Learn the business model. Understand how revenue is generated, what the major cost drivers are, and where your organization&amp;rsquo;s competitive advantages come from. You can&amp;rsquo;t optimize what you don&amp;rsquo;t understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Business Stakeholders:&lt;/strong&gt; Invest in basic data literacy. Not statistics or programming, but understanding what&amp;rsquo;s realistic versus science fiction. Most business leaders have unrealistic expectations about what data science can deliver and unrealistic timelines for delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Leadership:&lt;/strong&gt; Create accountability structures that reward business impact, not technical sophistication. If your data science team can&amp;rsquo;t explain their value in dollars, they&amp;rsquo;re probably not creating value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-success-actually-looks-like&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-success-actually-looks-like&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Success Actually Looks Like
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transformation isn&amp;rsquo;t measured by model accuracy or technical publications. It&amp;rsquo;s measured by whether business leaders fight for your team&amp;rsquo;s time instead of questioning your budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When data science teams truly align with business strategy, executives stop asking &amp;ldquo;What does the data science team actually do?&amp;rdquo; and start asking &amp;ldquo;How quickly can we expand this to other areas?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects move from PowerPoint to production because they&amp;rsquo;re designed for integration from day one. Teams stop defending their existence and start driving strategic discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-implementation-reality&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-implementation-reality&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Implementation Reality
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;My hope is that this provides a new lens for your own work, but let&amp;rsquo;s be realistic about the challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cultural change takes time. Technical teams resist business focus because it feels like compromising intellectual rigor. Business teams remain skeptical because they&amp;rsquo;ve been burned by previous &amp;ldquo;data initiatives&amp;rdquo; that promised transformation and delivered dashboards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The path forward requires persistent focus on problems that actually matter to the business, ruthless elimination of science projects, and obsessive attention to operational integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ultimate takeaway is this: the future belongs to organizations that turn data into better decisions, not organizations with the most sophisticated models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the most elegant algorithm in the world is worthless if it predicts failures of equipment that&amp;rsquo;s cheaper to run to failure anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop being a science project. Start being a strategic partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your budget - and your organization&amp;rsquo;s competitive advantage - depends on it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Ann Arbor&#39;s Energy Revolution: The Real Challenge Nobody&#39;s Talking About</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/seu-risk-analysis/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/seu-risk-analysis/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://192.168.100.63:1313/img/head/SEU.png" alt="Featured image of post Ann Arbor&#39;s Energy Revolution: The Real Challenge Nobody&#39;s Talking About" /&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ai-summary&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ai-summary&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI Summary
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ann Arbor launched America&amp;rsquo;s first true sustainable energy utility in 2024, winning 79% voter approval to build a parallel renewable energy system alongside the existing grid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The technical challenges of microgrid integration, customer onboarding, and grid interconnection are solvable - but the capital requirements are staggering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Successfully financing distributed infrastructure at scale remains the biggest unaddressed hurdle for community energy independence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This experiment will determine whether local energy systems can compete financially with centralized utilities, not just technically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-experiment-that-has-utilities-watching&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-experiment-that-has-utilities-watching&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Experiment That Has Utilities Watching
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ann Arbor just pulled off something that makes utility executives nervous: they convinced &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.canarymedia.com/articles/clean-energy/voters-in-ann-arbor-michigan-create-a-local-clean-energy-utility&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;79% of voters to approve&lt;/a&gt; creating their own supplemental energy system. Not just buying renewable energy credits or installing solar panels on city buildings - they&amp;rsquo;re building a parallel power infrastructure that could make them significantly less dependent on DTE Energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who&amp;rsquo;s spent years working in utility infrastructure, this has my complete attention. Not because the technology is revolutionary, but because Ann Arbor is tackling the one problem that kills most community energy projects before they start: how do you finance something this ambitious?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-ann-arbor-is-actually-building&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-ann-arbor-is-actually-building&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Ann Arbor Is Actually Building
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.a2gov.org/departments/sustainability/Sustainability-Me/Pages/Ann-Arbor%27s-Sustainable-Energy-Utility-%28SEU%29.aspx&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Sustainable Energy Utility (SEU)&lt;/a&gt; will provide solar and battery storage, energy waste reduction programs, and beneficial electrification support for individual households and businesses. But the real innovation isn&amp;rsquo;t in the hardware - it&amp;rsquo;s in the business model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan is to assemble an initial tranche of 20 megawatts worth of demand, at which point Ann Arbor will finance the purchase and installation of solar panels, batteries, and energy-efficiency upgrades to serve those customers. The city pays upfront for everything, owns the equipment, and recovers costs through energy sales to subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about what that means: Ann Arbor is essentially becoming a utility developer, equipment financier, and energy retailer all at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-capital-problem-everyone-ignores&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-capital-problem-everyone-ignores&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Capital Problem Everyone Ignores
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;While tech blogs focus on microgrid controllers and battery chemistry, they&amp;rsquo;re missing the real story. Every dollar we don&amp;rsquo;t spend in litigation or to buy the investor owned utility&amp;rsquo;s old, failing infrastructure is money we can spend on new infrastructure here in Ann Arbor, the city wrote in a 2021 report. That sounds great, but where exactly are those dollars coming from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s run some rough numbers. A 20 MW solar deployment with storage, plus customer-side efficiency upgrades, plus the infrastructure to interconnect everything? We&amp;rsquo;re talking about $40-60 million in upfront capital for the initial phase alone. While &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.a2gov.org/departments/sustainability/Sustainability-Me/Pages/Ann-Arbor%27s-Sustainable-Energy-Utility-%28SEU%29.aspx&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;residents may not see much regarding the deployment of SEU clean-energy assets for 18-24 months&lt;/a&gt;, the City of Ann Arbor is currently registering interest in the SEU - and they already have &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://energychangemakers.com/sustainable-energy-utility-launch-ann-arbor/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;600+ customers on the waitlist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s the real test: can a city of 120,000 people access the kind of capital markets that traditionally fund utility-scale infrastructure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-traditional-utility-finance-doesnt-work-here&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-traditional-utility-finance-doesnt-work-here&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why Traditional Utility Finance Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Work Here
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Investor-owned utilities have a straightforward financing model: they build infrastructure, regulators let them earn a return on that investment, and ratepayers cover the costs through monthly bills. It&amp;rsquo;s a guaranteed revenue stream backed by captive customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ann Arbor&amp;rsquo;s SEU has none of those advantages. It&amp;rsquo;s opt-in only, customers can leave anytime, and there&amp;rsquo;s no regulatory guarantee of cost recovery. From a lender&amp;rsquo;s perspective, it looks risky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even worse, the SEU&amp;rsquo;s final electricity rates will be &amp;ldquo;heavily influenced&amp;rdquo; by how many people sign up and what financing it gets. That creates a chicken-and-egg problem: you need customers to make the economics work, but you need good economics to attract customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-technical-challenges-are-actually-solvable&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-technical-challenges-are-actually-solvable&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Technical Challenges Are Actually Solvable
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong - building distributed energy systems is complex. Grid integration, customer onboarding logistics, and microgrid interconnection all require serious engineering. But these are known problems with proven solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community microgrids are already operating successfully in places like &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.microgridknowledge.com/google-news-feed/article/11429230/community-microgrids-four-examples-of-local-energy-that-improves-lives&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Blue Lake Rancheria in California&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.microgridknowledge.com/google-news-feed/article/11429230/community-microgrids-four-examples-of-local-energy-that-improves-lives&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Brooklyn&amp;rsquo;s Park Slope neighborhood&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.gencellenergy.com/resources/blog/microgrids-empower-communities-to-enjoy-sustainable-and-resilient-energy/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;rural communities across Alaska&lt;/a&gt;. The technology works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/ann-arbors-sustainable-energy-utility-aims-to-build-the-electric-power-grid-of-the-future-alongside-the-old-one-247189&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Ann Arbor&amp;rsquo;s sustainable energy utility doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to rely on old power lines&lt;/a&gt;, which actually simplifies things. Instead of retrofitting aging infrastructure, they&amp;rsquo;re building new systems designed from the ground up for renewable integration and two-way power flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real technical innovation is in the business model architecture: if a home generates more solar than it can use, it could run a line to a neighboring house that&amp;rsquo;s shaded by trees, allowing it to buy surplus power. That&amp;rsquo;s peer-to-peer energy trading backed by city-owned infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-success-looks-like-and-costs&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-success-looks-like-and-costs&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Success Looks Like (And Costs)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sustainable energy utility we&amp;rsquo;re creating is truly the first of its kind that is doing supplemental energy services only from renewables, according to Ann Arbor&amp;rsquo;s sustainability director. If it works, the benefits are compelling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lower costs through eliminated profit margins and reduced transmission expenses. Better reliability through distributed generation and storage. Community control over energy decisions instead of corporate boardroom choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But making it work requires solving problems that Silicon Valley startups and traditional utilities don&amp;rsquo;t face. How do you finance distributed infrastructure when your customers can leave? How do you scale operations without regulatory guarantees? How do you compete with incumbent utilities that can spread costs across captive ratepayers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-financing-innovation-nobodys-discussing&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-financing-innovation-nobodys-discussing&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Financing Innovation Nobody&amp;rsquo;s Discussing
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what makes Ann Arbor&amp;rsquo;s approach potentially game-changing: they&amp;rsquo;re treating energy infrastructure like municipal bonds instead of utility assets. &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.microgridknowledge.com/resources/microgrid-perspectives/article/55010904/schneider-electric-north-america-exploring-the-potential-of-community-microgrids-through-three-innovative-case-studies&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;KB Home&amp;rsquo;s groundbreaking Energy-Smart Connected Communities&lt;/a&gt; in Menifee, California, features over 200 cutting-edge, all-electric homes powered by solar energy and equipped with individual battery storage, supported by a &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.microgridknowledge.com/resources/microgrid-perspectives/article/55010904/schneider-electric-north-america-exploring-the-potential-of-community-microgrids-through-three-innovative-case-studies&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;$6.65 million Department of Energy grant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal grants, municipal bonds, and community investment could create a financing model that doesn&amp;rsquo;t depend on guaranteed returns or captive customers. Instead of traditional utility financing, think infrastructure investment backed by community commitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk is still real. If customer adoption is slower than projected, or if equipment costs run higher than expected, the city could face serious budget pressures. But if it works, Ann Arbor creates a template for community-controlled energy that other cities can replicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-this-matters-beyond-ann-arbor&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-this-matters-beyond-ann-arbor&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why This Matters Beyond Ann Arbor
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://annarborpublicpower.org/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;The group Ann Arbor for Public Power&lt;/a&gt; says, as long as the city continues to use DTE as its power utility, it won&amp;rsquo;t come close to reaching its goal of carbon neutrality by 2030. This frustration with incumbent utilities is spreading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364032119308950&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Community microgrids implemented in existing electricity grids&lt;/a&gt; can meet both development targets set out in the Paris agreement: mitigate greenhouse gas emissions through increased implementation of renewable energy sources, and adapt to climate related disturbances and risk of catastrophes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The precedent effect could be massive. If Ann Arbor proves that community-owned energy systems can work financially, not just technically, it changes the conversation about energy independence for every city dealing with unreliable or expensive utility service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-real-stakes&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-real-stakes&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Real Stakes
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This experiment isn&amp;rsquo;t really about solar panels and batteries. It&amp;rsquo;s about whether communities can control critical infrastructure without depending on distant corporations or regulatory capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ann Arbor has created a clear pathway to building more clean, local, resilient, and publicly owned infrastructure. If the city can make electricity cheaper on top of that, it will demonstrate that a better electricity system is possible even without completely overhauling the existing utility industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical challenges will get solved - smart people with good tools can figure out microgrid controllers and grid integration. The real question is whether innovative financing can make community energy systems economically sustainable at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-im-watching-for&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-im-watching-for&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;m Watching For
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Capital deployment speed: Can Ann Arbor actually access the $50+ million needed for the initial buildout without crippling municipal debt?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customer economics: Do the promised cost savings materialize when you factor in all the operational complexity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replication potential: If Ann Arbor succeeds, how quickly can other communities adopt similar models?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important infrastructure innovations often start at the local level. Ann Arbor&amp;rsquo;s energy experiment could be one of those innovations that changes how everyone thinks about power systems - but only if they can solve the capital problem that nobody&amp;rsquo;s talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current grid worked great for the 20th century. For the challenges of the 21st century - climate change, extreme weather, cybersecurity threats, and the need for rapid renewable energy adoption - we might need something different. Ann Arbor is betting they can build that something different, and finance it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of us should be paying very close attention to whether they can make the numbers work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Google&#39;s AI Weather Forecasters: The Future of Grid Resiliency?</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/gencast/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 14:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/gencast/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://192.168.100.63:1313/img/head/gencast.png" alt="Featured image of post Google&#39;s AI Weather Forecasters: The Future of Grid Resiliency?" /&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ai-summary&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ai-summary&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI Summary
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s GraphCast and GenCast models represent a fundamental shift from physics-based to AI-driven weather prediction, offering faster computation and potentially longer forecast horizons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GraphCast provides deterministic forecasts ideal for operational planning, while GenCast generates probabilistic ensembles crucial for risk management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For utilities, better weather prediction could transform storm response from reactive damage control to proactive grid hardening and crew positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration challenges remain significant, including system compatibility, operator training, and building trust in AI-generated forecasts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-old-guard-physics-vs-reality&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-old-guard-physics-vs-reality&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Old Guard: Physics vs. Reality
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weather is the single greatest threat to grid stability. From hurricanes tearing down transmission lines to heat domes pushing demand past breaking points, the ability to accurately predict weather isn&amp;rsquo;t just nice to have—it&amp;rsquo;s the foundation of keeping the lights on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, we&amp;rsquo;ve relied on traditional Numerical Weather Prediction (NWP) models. These are physics-based systems that attempt to solve the fundamental equations governing atmospheric behavior. They&amp;rsquo;re powerful, but they come with two major problems that anyone in utility operations knows intimately: they&amp;rsquo;re computationally expensive and they struggle with accuracy beyond 7-10 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re trying to decide whether to pre-position crews in western Pennsylvania or keep them local, that 7-day accuracy window can be the difference between restoring power in 2 hours versus 24 hours. After Riley, that distinction became more than academic—it became personal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graphcast-speed-meets-precision&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#graphcast-speed-meets-precision&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;GraphCast: Speed Meets Precision
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In late 2023, Google DeepMind unveiled &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/graphcast-ai-model-for-faster-and-more-accurate-global-weather-forecasting/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;GraphCast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and the meteorological community took notice. Published in the journal &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, this AI model demonstrated something unprecedented: it could predict global weather conditions up to 10 days out, faster and more accurately than the European Centre&amp;rsquo;s gold-standard HRES model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GraphCast doesn&amp;rsquo;t solve physics equations. Instead, it uses a Graph Neural Network that treats the entire planet as a massive, interconnected web of relationships. Trained on 40 years of historical weather data from the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.ecmwf.int/en/forecasts/dataset/ecmwf-reanalysis-v5&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;ERA5 dataset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, it learned to recognize patterns that traditional models miss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What GraphCast offers is something we desperately need in utility operations: a single, high-confidence prediction that we can build operational decisions around. When Winter Storm Riley was bearing down on us, we had multiple forecast models giving us different storm tracks, different wind speeds, and different timing. Making crew deployment decisions with that kind of uncertainty is like trying to hit a moving target while blindfolded. GraphCast&amp;rsquo;s deterministic approach could have changed everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;technical-performance&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#technical-performance&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Technical Performance
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The data from Google&amp;rsquo;s research speaks for itself. On 1380 weather variables, &lt;strong&gt;GraphCast outperformed the HRES system on more than 90% of the targets&lt;/strong&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a minor improvement; it&amp;rsquo;s a step-change in accuracy. The model&amp;rsquo;s prediction of Hurricane Lee&amp;rsquo;s path is a stark example, pinpointing landfall with greater accuracy and days more lead time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/DeepMind.com/Blog/graphcast-ai-model-for-faster-and-more-accurate-global-weather-forecasting/Graph_01_-_Still_-_Hi-Res.gif&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;GraphCast’s prediction of Hurricane Lee’s path, showing greater accuracy than traditional models.&#34;
	
	
&gt;
&lt;em&gt;GraphCast’s prediction for Hurricane Lee’s landfall (red) was more accurate than the traditional model (blue).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The root mean square error (RMSE) chart below shows GraphCast (in blue) consistently scoring lower (which is better) than the HRES model across various lead times and atmospheric levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/DeepMind.com/Blog/graphcast-ai-model-for-faster-and-more-accurate-global-weather-forecasting/rmse_lead_time_by_level.png&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;A chart showing GraphCast’s lower root mean square error (RMSE) compared to the HRES model across various lead times.&#34;
	
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gencast-embracing-uncertainty&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#gencast-embracing-uncertainty&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;GenCast: Embracing Uncertainty
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the thing about weather: the future is inherently uncertain. That&amp;rsquo;s where &lt;strong&gt;GenCast&lt;/strong&gt;, Google&amp;rsquo;s more recent innovation, becomes truly interesting for grid operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GenCast is a diffusion model—the same class of AI that creates hyper-realistic images—but instead of generating pictures, it generates possible futures. Given current weather conditions, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t produce one forecast; it creates an &lt;strong&gt;ensemble of dozens of plausible scenarios&lt;/strong&gt;, each with associated probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probabilistic approach addresses something that keeps utility executives awake at night: &lt;em&gt;What if we&amp;rsquo;re wrong?&lt;/em&gt; For grid planning, this is revolutionary. Instead of preparing for one scenario, you can prepare for a range of outcomes weighted by their likelihood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;technical-performance-1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#technical-performance-1&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Technical Performance
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;GenCast&amp;rsquo;s strength lies in its ability to generate sharp, reliable, and diverse ensembles. It achieves state-of-the-art (SOTA) accuracy on both deterministic and probabilistic metrics. For probabilistic forecasting, the key metric is the Continuous Ranked Probability Score (CRPS), where lower is better. &lt;strong&gt;GenCast demonstrates a significant improvement in CRPS over the ECMWF-ENS ensemble&lt;/strong&gt;, especially for longer lead times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/DeepMind.com/Blog/gencast-predicts-weather-and-the-risks-of-extreme-conditions-with-sota-accuracy/GenCast-CRPS.png&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;A chart showing GenCast’s superior (lower) CRPS score compared to the traditional ECMWF ensemble model.&#34;
	
	
&gt;
&lt;em&gt;GenCast consistently achieves a better (lower) CRPS than the benchmark ECMWF ensemble model, particularly at longer forecast horizons.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This allows for much better risk assessment of extreme weather. Instead of a single storm track, GenCast provides a &amp;ldquo;cone of uncertainty&amp;rdquo; that is based on a diverse set of high-fidelity simulations, giving operators a much clearer picture of what could happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/DeepMind.com/Blog/gencast-predicts-weather-and-the-risks-of-extreme-conditions-with-sota-accuracy/GenCast-AR-3.gif&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;An image showing GenCast’s probabilistic forecast for an atmospheric river event, displaying multiple potential paths.&#34;
	
	
&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A GenCast ensemble forecast for an atmospheric river, showing multiple high-resolution potential scenarios.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ai-vs-ai-a-tale-of-two-forecasters&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ai-vs-ai-a-tale-of-two-forecasters&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI vs. AI: A Tale of Two Forecasters
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;These models are not competitors; they are complementary tools for a modern utility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Feature&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GraphCast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GenCast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model Type&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Graph Neural Network (GNN)&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Diffusion Model&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Output&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deterministic:&lt;/strong&gt; A single, high-accuracy forecast.&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Probabilistic:&lt;/strong&gt; An ensemble of possible future scenarios.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best For&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operational Planning:&lt;/strong&gt; Direct, day-to-day decisions (e.g., crew deployment).&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategic Risk Management:&lt;/strong&gt; Assessing the range of possibilities and worst-case scenarios.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Question Answered&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;What is the most likely weather outcome?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;What are all the possible weather outcomes and how likely are they?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-integration-reality-check&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-integration-reality-check&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Integration Reality Check
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the promise, integrating these AI models into utility operations isn&amp;rsquo;t trivial. The power industry operates with legacy systems, deeply ingrained procedures, and regulatory oversight that doesn&amp;rsquo;t move quickly. The technical challenges are significant, including adapting our software to ingest probabilistic forecasts and training our operators to trust—but also verify—the AI&amp;rsquo;s output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;black box&amp;rdquo; problem is real. In an industry where lives and billions of dollars of infrastructure are on the line, trusting a forecast you don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand is a hard sell. This requires a human-in-the-loop approach where experts can always challenge the AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-proactive-grid&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-proactive-grid&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Proactive Grid
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we can solve the integration challenges, the impact on grid reliability will be transformative. Imagine having 15 days of accurate notice before an extreme weather event. We could proactively de-energize high-risk lines, position crews based on probabilistic damage assessments, and make our renewable energy sources far more predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This represents a fundamental shift from emergency response to strategic preparation. After experiencing storms like Riley, where we spent days scrambling to restore service, the appeal of that kind of foresight is impossible to overstate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-trust-in-silicon-and-circuits&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#building-trust-in-silicon-and-circuits&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Building Trust in Silicon and Circuits
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The future of grid management won&amp;rsquo;t be run by autonomous AI, but by human experts armed with unprecedentedly clear views of what&amp;rsquo;s coming. GraphCast and GenCast aren&amp;rsquo;t replacements for meteorologists and grid operators—they&amp;rsquo;re force multipliers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my role overseeing data science for grid operations, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that the most sophisticated model is worthless if operators don&amp;rsquo;t trust it or understand how to act on its insights. The real challenge isn&amp;rsquo;t building better AI; it&amp;rsquo;s building systems that make human experts more effective. Better weather forecasting isn&amp;rsquo;t just a technical achievement; it&amp;rsquo;s a pathway to a more resilient society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s AI weather models represent a monumental leap forward. In an era of increasing climate volatility, that clarity might be the most critical infrastructure we can build.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
