<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science, Strategy, Leadership on My Blog</title>
    <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Science, Strategy, Leadership on My Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 03:00:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why &#39;The Smartest Person in the Room&#39; is Killing Your Data Science Team</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/genius/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 03:00:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/genius/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why &amp;lsquo;The Smartest Person in the Room&amp;rsquo; is Killing Your Data Science Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every data science leader has met them—the brilliant individual who can solve problems no one else can crack, who knows the codebase inside out, who seems to have every algorithm memorized, and who can debug the most complex models in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re the hero, the go-to person, the one who pulls off miracles when deadlines loom. They&amp;rsquo;re the smartest person in the room.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Scale a Data Science Team Without Losing Agility</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/agility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/agility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-to-scale-a-data-science-team-without-losing-agility&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Scale a Data Science Team Without Losing Agility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched dozens of data science teams follow the same painful trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They start small—three or four talented individuals moving fast, shipping models, and delivering insights that make the business take notice. Leadership gets excited. Budgets expand. Headcount doubles, then doubles again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And then, somehow, everything grinds to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The team that once deployed models in weeks now takes months. Projects that used to flow seamlessly now get bogged down in meetings and documentation. The scrappy, high-impact group has transformed into a sluggish bureaucracy that spends more time managing processes than delivering value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Business Leaders Get Wrong About Data Science (And How to Educate Them)</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/leaders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/leaders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-business-leaders-get-wrong-about-data-science-and-how-to-educate-them&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Business Leaders Get Wrong About Data Science (And How to Educate Them)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve sat through hundreds of meetings where business leaders talk about data science like it&amp;rsquo;s magic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Can&amp;rsquo;t we just use AI to predict which customers will churn?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s build a model that tells us exactly what products to develop next.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I heard Company X increased revenue by 40% with machine learning—we should do that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The enthusiasm is great. The understanding? Not so much.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Align Data Science with Business Strategy (And Stop Being a Science Project Team)</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/businessstrategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:36:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/businessstrategy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-to-align-data-science-with-business-strategy-and-stop-being-a-science-project-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Align Data Science with Business Strategy (And Stop Being a Science Project Team)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data science teams often find themselves in a frustrating position: technically brilliant but strategically irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it countless times. Teams of PhDs and talented engineers building sophisticated models that never see the light of day. Data scientists spending months on projects that executives don&amp;rsquo;t understand or care about. Analytics capabilities that impress at conferences but fail to move the business forward.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Managing Tech Debt: How to Stop Paying the Interest and Start Building for Scale</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/techdebt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/techdebt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;managing-tech-debt-how-to-stop-paying-the-interest-and-start-building-for-scale&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Tech Debt: How to Stop Paying the Interest and Start Building for Scale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tech debt isn’t a failure—it’s a fact of life.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every company, every team, and every project accrues tech debt in some form. The real question isn’t &lt;strong&gt;how to avoid it completely&lt;/strong&gt; (because you won’t), but &lt;strong&gt;how to manage it so it doesn’t cripple your ability to deliver.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In data science, tech debt comes from &lt;strong&gt;unreproducible code, lack of standardization, ignoring MLOps, poor data governance, and overcomplicated models.&lt;/strong&gt; In tech more broadly, it happens when teams &lt;strong&gt;over-customize applications, hack together one-off solutions, and fail to think about long-term infrastructure.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 80/20 Rule of Data Science: Focus on What Actually Moves the Needle</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/8020rule/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/8020rule/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-8020-rule-of-data-science-focus-on-what-actually-moves-the-needle&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 80/20 Rule of Data Science: Focus on What Actually Moves the Needle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest mistakes data science teams make is &lt;strong&gt;spending too much time on the wrong things.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to fall into the trap of optimizing a model for another 0.2% accuracy, building complex pipelines for edge cases, or experimenting endlessly without delivering real impact. But &lt;strong&gt;the harsh reality is that 80% of business impact comes from just 20% of the work.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building High Impact Data Science Teams</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/foundations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/foundations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;building-high-impact-data-science-teams-avoiding-the-tech-debt-trap-and-driving-real-business-value&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building High-Impact Data Science Teams: Avoiding the Tech Debt Trap and Driving Real Business Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants a high-impact data science team. But too often, companies end up with a &lt;strong&gt;high-cost, low-output, tech-debt-ridden mess&lt;/strong&gt; that looks great in a slide deck but doesn’t actually move the business forward.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen teams over-index on hiring the &lt;strong&gt;smartest person in the room&lt;/strong&gt;, chase cutting-edge models that add complexity without value, and burn months on projects that never get adopted. The difference between a &lt;strong&gt;high-impact&lt;/strong&gt; data science function and a &lt;strong&gt;high-friction&lt;/strong&gt; one usually comes down to a few key things: &lt;strong&gt;vision, execution, and integration.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
