<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>About Me on The Patch Panel</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/about/</link>
        <description>Recent content in About Me on The Patch Panel</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>About Me</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/about/about/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/about/about/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey there! I&amp;rsquo;m Ben—a husband and proud dad first and foremost. My wife and I share our life with two amazing little humans: our curious and energetic 4-year-old son, and our sweet, adventurous 1-year-old daughter. They&amp;rsquo;re my world and keep me happily busy, endlessly entertained, and constantly inspired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m not in full-on dad mode, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably find me deeply immersed in my homelab. My basement hums gently with servers, virtual machines, and containers, where I geek out over advanced networking setups, robust automation, and cutting-edge AI workflows. I&amp;rsquo;m currently exploring some exciting development projects around generative AI, automation frameworks, and personal productivity dashboards—always looking for innovative ways to bridge tech and daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside the tech realm, I have a deep appreciation for historic architecture—I proudly own and continually renovate an 1800s farmhouse in southeastern Pennsylvania, near Philadelphia. On our 10 acres of land, I enjoy tending to the property, maintaining gardens, and caring for an ever-growing collection of cactuses (yes, even in Pennsylvania!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also a passionate sports fan: you can often find me cheering for the Pittsburgh Penguins during hockey season and rooting for Penn State Football every fall. And when I can carve out some free time, you&amp;rsquo;ll catch me in the garage working on my modified BMW 135i—another ongoing project that keeps my hands busy and my mind engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professionally, I&amp;rsquo;ve spent over a decade leading high-performing data science teams at large companies and federal agencies. My focus is always on bridging the gap between complex technology and real-world business impact—making sure our work actually matters, not just dazzles. I&amp;rsquo;ve built analytics organizations from scratch, managed multimillion-dollar budgets, and navigated the tricky waters of enterprise strategy and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At my core, though, I&amp;rsquo;m driven by curiosity. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s homelab tinkering, exploring AI breakthroughs, restoring historic charm, or fine-tuning cars, I’m always looking for ways to grow, optimize, and build things that matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for stopping by my little digital corner. I’m glad you&amp;rsquo;re here—feel free to reach out, ask questions, or just say hi!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
