<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning on My Blog</title>
    <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Machine Learning on My Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Gemma 3: Google&#39;s Lean, Mean AI Machine Takes on DeepSeek V3</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/gemma3-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/gemma3-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;gemma-3-googles-lean-mean-ai-machine-takes-on-deepseek-v3&#34;&gt;Gemma 3: Google&amp;rsquo;s Lean, Mean AI Machine Takes on DeepSeek V3&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Google just dropped a bombshell in the AI community with the release of &lt;strong&gt;Gemma 3&lt;/strong&gt;, touting it as the most powerful AI model you can run on a single GPU. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just another incremental update; it&amp;rsquo;s a potential game-changer in how we think about AI efficiency and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-this-matters&#34;&gt;Why This Matters&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, achieving top-tier AI performance has required massive computational resources—think server farms packed with high-end GPUs. This not only limits who can develop and deploy advanced models but also raises concerns about energy consumption and environmental impact. Gemma 3 flips the script by delivering comparable performance using significantly fewer resources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Reality Check of GPT-5: When AI Ambitions Meet Practical Constraints</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/gpt5-future-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/gpt5-future-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-reality-check-of-gpt-5-when-ai-ambitions-meet-practical-constraints&#34;&gt;The Reality Check of GPT-5: When AI Ambitions Meet Practical Constraints&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s much-anticipated GPT-5 project, codenamed &amp;ldquo;Orion,&amp;rdquo; has faced unexpected hurdles. Despite high expectations for a radical leap in AI capabilities, the project has encountered delays due to data limitations, escalating costs, and operational challenges. This serves as a crucial reminder that AI progress is neither linear nor guaranteed. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/openai-gpt5-orion-delays-639e7693?utm_source=chatgpt.com&#34;&gt;Read full article&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-gpt-5-is-struggling&#34;&gt;Why GPT-5 Is Struggling&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At its core, the challenges surrounding GPT-5 highlight a fundamental truth about AI: at a certain scale, improvement is no longer just a function of adding more compute and data. OpenAI is grappling with issues such as:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
