<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>United States on My Blog</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63/tags/united-states/</link>
        <description>Recent content in United States on My Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63/tags/united-states/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>The Cybersecurity Misdirection: Why Ignoring Russia is a Risky Move</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63/musings/cybersecurity-thoughts/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63/musings/cybersecurity-thoughts/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;we-just-stopped-watching-russia-and-thats-terrifying&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#we-just-stopped-watching-russia-and-thats-terrifying&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;We Just Stopped Watching Russia and That&amp;rsquo;s Terrifying
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why treating cybersecurity like a popularity contest is incredibly dangerous&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So apparently the U.S. has decided that Russia just isn&amp;rsquo;t that interesting anymore from a cybersecurity perspective. The new plan is to focus on China instead, because apparently we can only worry about one major cyber threat at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feels like deciding to ignore one armed robber because you spotted another one across the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-logic-that-makes-no-sense&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-logic-that-makes-no-sense&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Logic That Makes No Sense
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the thinking: China is becoming the bigger cyber threat, so let&amp;rsquo;s shift our attention there and deprioritize Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On paper, this might sound reasonable.&lt;/strong&gt; China is definitely expanding their cyber capabilities. They&amp;rsquo;re stealing intellectual property, conducting espionage, and building sophisticated attack infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In reality, this is incredibly naive.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cyber threats don&amp;rsquo;t work like a video game where you can pause one boss fight to handle another. Russia didn&amp;rsquo;t suddenly become harmless because China got more attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;russia-didnt-get-the-memo&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#russia-didnt-get-the-memo&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Russia Didn&amp;rsquo;t Get the Memo
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about Russia&amp;rsquo;s greatest hits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SolarWinds hack&lt;/strong&gt; - Compromised 18,000 organizations including multiple government agencies
&lt;strong&gt;NotPetya attacks&lt;/strong&gt; - Caused billions in damage to global infrastructure&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Election interference&lt;/strong&gt; - Ongoing operations targeting democratic processes
&lt;strong&gt;Colonial Pipeline&lt;/strong&gt; - Shut down critical energy infrastructure&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These weren&amp;rsquo;t pranks or amateur hour operations. They were sophisticated, coordinated attacks that had real consequences for national security and the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the kicker:&lt;/strong&gt; None of this stopped when we decided China was more important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-burglar-analogy&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-burglar-analogy&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Burglar Analogy
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imagine you know someone&amp;rsquo;s been trying to break into your house for years. They&amp;rsquo;ve already gotten in a few times, stolen things, left nasty surprises. You&amp;rsquo;ve seen them casing the place, testing your locks, learning your routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you hear about break-ins happening across town by a different group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you:
A) Stop locking your doors because the other group seems more active lately
B) Secure your house against both threats&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, U.S. cybersecurity policy chose option A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-could-go-wrong-spoiler-everything&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-could-go-wrong-spoiler-everything&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Could Go Wrong (Spoiler: Everything)
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-unchecked-russian-activity&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#more-unchecked-russian-activity&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;More Unchecked Russian Activity
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you stop actively monitoring and deterring a threat, that threat doesn&amp;rsquo;t disappear. It gets bolder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia&amp;rsquo;s cyber units are still operational, still funded, still looking for opportunities. Less attention from the U.S. means more room for them to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;coordinated-attacks&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#coordinated-attacks&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Coordinated Attacks
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia and China don&amp;rsquo;t need to be best friends to find common ground in weakening U.S. infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens when they decide to coordinate attacks? While we&amp;rsquo;re focused on defending against Chinese espionage, Russian hackers could be setting up infrastructure attacks. Or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reactive-instead-of-proactive-defense&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#reactive-instead-of-proactive-defense&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Reactive Instead of Proactive Defense
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of preventing attacks, we&amp;rsquo;ll be responding to them after the damage is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario:&lt;/strong&gt; Russian hackers target power grids while everyone&amp;rsquo;s focused on Chinese intellectual property theft. By the time we realize what&amp;rsquo;s happening, the lights are already out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-internet-doesnt-care-about-our-priorities&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-internet-doesnt-care-about-our-priorities&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Internet Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Care About Our Priorities
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what cybersecurity experts understand that policymakers apparently don&amp;rsquo;t:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cyber threats are simultaneous, not sequential.&lt;/strong&gt; You can&amp;rsquo;t pause one while dealing with another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attack infrastructure stays active regardless of political focus.&lt;/strong&gt; Russian hacker groups didn&amp;rsquo;t shut down their operations when the U.S. shifted priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deterrence requires consistent attention.&lt;/strong&gt; The moment you signal that a threat isn&amp;rsquo;t a priority, you invite escalation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defense requires comprehensive coverage.&lt;/strong&gt; You can&amp;rsquo;t just defend against the threat you&amp;rsquo;re most worried about this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-really-means&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-this-really-means&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What This Really Means
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-government-systems&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#for-government-systems&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For Government Systems
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Critical infrastructure becomes more vulnerable to Russian attacks while defenses focus elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-private-companies&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#for-private-companies&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For Private Companies
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Businesses may deprioritize Russian threat intelligence, leaving them exposed to attacks they&amp;rsquo;re not monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;for-national-security&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#for-national-security&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For National Security
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re essentially telling Russia that they have more room to operate as long as they stay out of the spotlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-smarter-approach&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-smarter-approach&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Smarter Approach
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recognize that both threats are active simultaneously&lt;/strong&gt;
China and Russia aren&amp;rsquo;t taking turns attacking U.S. systems. They&amp;rsquo;re both active all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invest in comprehensive defense capabilities&lt;/strong&gt;
Build systems that can detect and respond to multiple threat actors simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintain intelligence operations on all major adversaries&lt;/strong&gt;
Just because one threat seems more pressing doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you stop watching the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coordinate international responses&lt;/strong&gt;
Work with allies who may have different threat priorities to maintain coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-feels-personal&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-this-feels-personal&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why This Feels Personal
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched cybersecurity evolve from an IT afterthought to a national security priority. The progress has been slow but real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This decision feels like a step backward.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the kind of thinking that led to major breaches in the past - assuming that threats are predictable, manageable, and mutually exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality is messier. Cyber warfare doesn&amp;rsquo;t follow neat rules or take turns. Multiple adversaries operate simultaneously, often exploiting exactly the kind of attention gaps we&amp;rsquo;re creating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bottom-line&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-bottom-line&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Bottom Line
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cybersecurity isn&amp;rsquo;t a zero-sum game.&lt;/strong&gt; Focusing on China doesn&amp;rsquo;t require ignoring Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threat actors don&amp;rsquo;t respect our priority lists.&lt;/strong&gt; Russia&amp;rsquo;s capabilities didn&amp;rsquo;t diminish just because we decided China was more important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defense requires comprehensive coverage.&lt;/strong&gt; You can&amp;rsquo;t just defend against this week&amp;rsquo;s favorite threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History suggests this will backfire.&lt;/strong&gt; Every time we&amp;rsquo;ve underestimated or deprioritized a cyber adversary, we&amp;rsquo;ve paid for it later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet has no borders, and cyber warfare doesn&amp;rsquo;t operate on a ranking system. Treating national cybersecurity like we can only handle one major threat at a time is dangerously naive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China is absolutely a serious cyber threat that deserves attention and resources.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So is Russia.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We need to be capable of handling both simultaneously.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I guarantee you, they&amp;rsquo;re both planning to handle us simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In cybersecurity, the cost of getting it wrong isn&amp;rsquo;t just embarrassment or lost data - it&amp;rsquo;s national security. We can&amp;rsquo;t afford to play favorites with threats that don&amp;rsquo;t play by our rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
