<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Leadership on My Blog</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63/categories/leadership/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Leadership on My Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 13:37:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63/categories/leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>What My 1 and 4-Year-Olds Taught Me About Leading Data Teams</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63/datascience/kids/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 13:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63/datascience/kids/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-kids-accidentally-made-me-a-better-data-leader&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#my-kids-accidentally-made-me-a-better-data-leader&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;My Kids Accidentally Made Me a Better Data Leader
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What a 1-year-old and 4-year-old taught me about managing teams&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I had leadership figured out. Read all the right books, attended the workshops, considered myself pretty good with people. Then I became a dad and realized I knew absolutely nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 1-year-old daughter and 4-year-old son don&amp;rsquo;t care about my MBA or how many data scientists I&amp;rsquo;ve managed. They just want me to understand them, be curious with them, and not lose my mind when things go sideways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what my data teams needed too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After four years of fumbling through both parenting and leadership simultaneously, I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered that toddlers make surprisingly good leadership coaches. They&amp;rsquo;ve completely changed how I think about empathy, curiosity, and creating safe spaces for people to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what they taught me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lesson-1-actually-listen-before-you-try-to-fix-everything&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#lesson-1-actually-listen-before-you-try-to-fix-everything&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lesson 1: Actually Listen Before You Try to Fix Everything
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My 1-year-old can&amp;rsquo;t tell me what&amp;rsquo;s wrong when she&amp;rsquo;s upset. She just cries. So I&amp;rsquo;ve become a detective - is she hungry? Tired? Frustrated that she can&amp;rsquo;t reach her toy? I have to put aside whatever I was doing and really pay attention to understand what she needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This completely changed how I handle team problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before kids:&lt;/strong&gt; Someone comes to me with an issue, I immediately start problem-solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After kids:&lt;/strong&gt; I force myself to understand first, solve second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of jumping to solutions, I started asking things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Help me understand what you&amp;rsquo;re experiencing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s the most frustrating part of this for you?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Walk me through how this feels from your perspective&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference has been huge. When we actually understand the real problem - not just the surface symptoms - our solutions actually work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One data scientist came to me complaining about &amp;ldquo;technical debt in our models.&amp;rdquo; My old approach would have been to immediately discuss refactoring strategies. Instead, I asked her to help me understand what she was experiencing day-to-day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out the real issue wasn&amp;rsquo;t technical debt - it was that she felt like her work wasn&amp;rsquo;t valued because leadership kept asking for quick fixes instead of letting her build things properly. Completely different problem, completely different solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lesson-2-ask-why-like-your-job-depends-on-it&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#lesson-2-ask-why-like-your-job-depends-on-it&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lesson 2: Ask &amp;ldquo;Why&amp;rdquo; Like Your Job Depends on It
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My 4-year-old asks &amp;ldquo;why&amp;rdquo; about everything. And I mean everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why is the sky blue?&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Why do cars have wheels?&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Why do we brush our teeth?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s exhausting, but it&amp;rsquo;s also brilliant. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t accept &amp;ldquo;that&amp;rsquo;s just how things are&amp;rdquo; as an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started bringing that same energy to work, and it&amp;rsquo;s been a game-changer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In strategy meetings, I became the annoying person asking:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why do we structure our data this way?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why is this the process we follow?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why do we think this approach is best?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, people were a bit put off. These questions can feel naive when you&amp;rsquo;re deep in expertise. But they&amp;rsquo;ve led to some of our biggest breakthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One simple &amp;ldquo;why do we run this report weekly instead of daily?&amp;rdquo; led us to redesign the entire process and improve data freshness by 80%. Sometimes the most basic questions unlock the biggest improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now schedule &amp;ldquo;fundamental questioning&amp;rdquo; sessions quarterly where we deliberately challenge our basic assumptions. The only rule: every &amp;ldquo;why&amp;rdquo; gets a real answer, not defensiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lesson-3-learn-stuff-together-even-when-you-dont-know-the-answer&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#lesson-3-learn-stuff-together-even-when-you-dont-know-the-answer&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lesson 3: Learn Stuff Together (Even When You Don&amp;rsquo;t Know the Answer)
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watching my daughter discover shadows for the first time, or my son realize he can mix colors to make new ones - the pure joy of discovery is infectious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the thing: I&amp;rsquo;m learning right alongside them. I don&amp;rsquo;t have all the answers about why leaves change color or how airplanes stay up. We figure it out together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This completely changed how I approach new challenges at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instead of feeling like I need to be the expert on everything, I started saying:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know, let&amp;rsquo;s figure it out together.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we needed to implement a new computer vision system, instead of bringing in external consultants, I formed a learning team. I participated not as the leader with all the answers, but as someone equally curious about how this technology worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project took a bit longer than it might have with outside experts, but something amazing happened - the entire team&amp;rsquo;s confidence and capability grew exponentially. They owned the solution because they built it together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best leaders I know aren&amp;rsquo;t the ones with the most expertise. They&amp;rsquo;re the ones who create environments where everyone gets to discover and learn together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lesson-4-make-it-safe-to-mess-up&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#lesson-4-make-it-safe-to-mess-up&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lesson 4: Make It Safe to Mess Up
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My son built this elaborate castle out of magnetic tiles last week. Spent 30 minutes on it, was so proud. Then he accidentally knocked it over while reaching for something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was ready for a meltdown. Instead, he looked at the pieces and said, &amp;ldquo;Now I can build something even cooler!&amp;rdquo; and started over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That resilience didn&amp;rsquo;t happen overnight. It developed because we&amp;rsquo;ve always treated mistakes as learning opportunities, not disasters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized my data teams needed that same psychological safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I started being more open about my own mistakes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sharing my &amp;ldquo;learning moments&amp;rdquo; in team meetings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running &amp;ldquo;failure retrospectives&amp;rdquo; focused on what we learned, not who screwed up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celebrating bold attempts, even when they didn&amp;rsquo;t work out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After one particularly visible project failure, instead of looking for someone to blame, I guided the team through a learning-focused retrospective. The insights from that session informed our next attempt, which became one of our most successful initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, people started proposing bolder ideas because they weren&amp;rsquo;t afraid of being punished for trying something that might not work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-changed-and-what-it-actually-looks-like&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-changed-and-what-it-actually-looks-like&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Changed (And What It Actually Looks Like)
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;before-kids-the-expert-approach&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#before-kids-the-expert-approach&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Before Kids (The &amp;ldquo;Expert&amp;rdquo; Approach)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jump straight to solutions when people bring problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel pressure to have all the answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on individual performance and expertise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treat mistakes as problems to be avoided&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-kids-the-human-approach&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#after-kids-the-human-approach&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;After Kids (The &amp;ldquo;Human&amp;rdquo; Approach)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen first, understand the real problem, then solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comfortable saying &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know, let&amp;rsquo;s learn together&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on team learning and collective capability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treat mistakes as opportunities to get better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-practical-results&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-practical-results&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Practical Results
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Employee satisfaction around &amp;ldquo;feeling heard&amp;rdquo; went up 42%&lt;/strong&gt; in six months after we implemented the &amp;ldquo;understand first&amp;rdquo; approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation attempts increased significantly&lt;/strong&gt; after we created psychological safety around failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team capability grew faster&lt;/strong&gt; when we learned new technologies together instead of always bringing in outside experts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better solutions&lt;/strong&gt; emerged when we actually understood problems before trying to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-uncomfortable-truth-about-technical-leadership&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-uncomfortable-truth-about-technical-leadership&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Uncomfortable Truth About Technical Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what parenting taught me that all the leadership books missed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical expertise isn&amp;rsquo;t what makes great leaders.&lt;/strong&gt; The ability to create environments where people feel understood, curious, and safe to try things - that&amp;rsquo;s what makes great leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The smartest person in the room isn&amp;rsquo;t always the best leader.&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes the best leader is the person asking the most basic questions or admitting they don&amp;rsquo;t know something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation requires psychological safety.&lt;/strong&gt; People won&amp;rsquo;t propose creative solutions if they&amp;rsquo;re afraid of looking stupid or being blamed when things don&amp;rsquo;t work perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real empathy is work.&lt;/strong&gt; It means putting aside your own agenda and really trying to understand someone else&amp;rsquo;s experience. It&amp;rsquo;s harder than technical problem-solving, but it&amp;rsquo;s what actually moves teams forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-looks-like-in-practice&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-this-looks-like-in-practice&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What This Looks Like in Practice
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;start-every-problem-conversation-with-understanding&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#start-every-problem-conversation-with-understanding&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Start Every Problem Conversation with Understanding
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of: &amp;ldquo;Here&amp;rsquo;s how we should fix this&amp;rdquo;
Try: &amp;ldquo;Help me understand what you&amp;rsquo;re experiencing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ask-fundamental-questions-regularly&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ask-fundamental-questions-regularly&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ask Fundamental Questions Regularly
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of: Accepting &amp;ldquo;that&amp;rsquo;s how we&amp;rsquo;ve always done it&amp;rdquo;
Try: &amp;ldquo;Why is this the best approach for what we&amp;rsquo;re trying to achieve?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;learn-alongside-your-team&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#learn-alongside-your-team&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Learn Alongside Your Team
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll bring in an expert to teach you&amp;rdquo;
Try: &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know this either - let&amp;rsquo;s figure it out together&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;make-failure-safe&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#make-failure-safe&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Make Failure Safe
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of: &amp;ldquo;Who made this mistake?&amp;rdquo;
Try: &amp;ldquo;What can we learn from this that will help us next time?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bottom-line&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-bottom-line&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Bottom Line
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My kids don&amp;rsquo;t care about my technical credentials or management philosophy. They just want me to pay attention, be curious, and create a safe space for them to grow and explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what data teams need too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best technical leaders aren&amp;rsquo;t the ones with the most expertise - they&amp;rsquo;re the ones who can create environments where everyone feels heard, stays curious, and isn&amp;rsquo;t afraid to try new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if your leadership approach feels stale, maybe the best teachers aren&amp;rsquo;t in the boardroom or business books. Maybe they&amp;rsquo;re the ones asking &amp;ldquo;why&amp;rdquo; for the hundredth time today while building something amazing out of blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Four years into this parenting and leadership journey, I&amp;rsquo;m convinced that the soft skills matter way more than the technical ones. My kids keep teaching me that every day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
