<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Team Building on My Blog</title>
    <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/team-building/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Team Building on My Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:59:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/team-building/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How to Scale a Data Science Team Without Losing Agility</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/agility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/agility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-to-scale-a-data-science-team-without-losing-agility&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Scale a Data Science Team Without Losing Agility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched dozens of data science teams follow the same painful trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They start small—three or four talented individuals moving fast, shipping models, and delivering insights that make the business take notice. Leadership gets excited. Budgets expand. Headcount doubles, then doubles again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And then, somehow, everything grinds to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The team that once deployed models in weeks now takes months. Projects that used to flow seamlessly now get bogged down in meetings and documentation. The scrappy, high-impact group has transformed into a sluggish bureaucracy that spends more time managing processes than delivering value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building High Impact Data Science Teams</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/foundations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/foundations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;building-high-impact-data-science-teams-avoiding-the-tech-debt-trap-and-driving-real-business-value&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building High-Impact Data Science Teams: Avoiding the Tech Debt Trap and Driving Real Business Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants a high-impact data science team. But too often, companies end up with a &lt;strong&gt;high-cost, low-output, tech-debt-ridden mess&lt;/strong&gt; that looks great in a slide deck but doesn’t actually move the business forward.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen teams over-index on hiring the &lt;strong&gt;smartest person in the room&lt;/strong&gt;, chase cutting-edge models that add complexity without value, and burn months on projects that never get adopted. The difference between a &lt;strong&gt;high-impact&lt;/strong&gt; data science function and a &lt;strong&gt;high-friction&lt;/strong&gt; one usually comes down to a few key things: &lt;strong&gt;vision, execution, and integration.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
