<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Productivity on The Patch Panel</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/productivity/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Productivity on The Patch Panel</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 14:30:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Beyond &#39;Tell Me About&#39;: A Guide to Advanced Prompt Engineering</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/ai/prompting/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 14:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/ai/prompting/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://192.168.100.63:1313/img/head/prompting.png" alt="Featured image of post Beyond &#39;Tell Me About&#39;: A Guide to Advanced Prompt Engineering" /&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ai-summary&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ai-summary&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI Summary
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chain-of-thought prompting forces AI to show its reasoning process step-by-step, dramatically improving accuracy on complex problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prompt chaining breaks large projects into focused workflows where each AI response feeds into the next prompt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structured output formats like JSON or Markdown tables make AI responses immediately usable in other applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;ldquo;committee of experts&amp;rdquo; technique simulates multi-perspective debates to uncover nuanced insights and balanced analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-architects-advantage&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-architects-advantage&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Architect&amp;rsquo;s Advantage
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last time I watched someone struggle with AI, they were firing off question after question, getting increasingly frustrated with the lukewarm responses. &amp;ldquo;Write me a marketing plan,&amp;rdquo; they&amp;rsquo;d say, then frown at the generic bullet points that came back. They knew &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; was missing, but couldn&amp;rsquo;t put their finger on what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the pivot point where casual AI users and true power users diverge. The difference isn&amp;rsquo;t in the complexity of the questions - it&amp;rsquo;s in understanding that you&amp;rsquo;re not just asking for answers. You&amp;rsquo;re designing the AI&amp;rsquo;s thought process itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After wrestling with this problem across dozens of projects, a pattern emerged. The most valuable AI interactions happen when you stop being a questioner and start being an architect. You&amp;rsquo;re not just extracting information; you&amp;rsquo;re constructing a framework for how the AI should think, reason, and respond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chain-of-thought-making-the-invisible-visible&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#chain-of-thought-making-the-invisible-visible&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chain-of-Thought: Making the Invisible Visible
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conventional wisdom about AI accuracy is starting to show its cracks. We&amp;rsquo;ve been taught that these systems are either right or wrong, but the reality is more nuanced. The quality of reasoning matters as much as the final answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chain-of-thought prompting forces the AI to externalize its reasoning process. Instead of jumping to conclusions, it must show its work. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just pedagogical theater - it fundamentally changes how the AI approaches problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A farmer has 15 animals (chickens and pigs) with a total of 44 legs. How many of each does he have? Let&amp;rsquo;s think step by step.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic happens in that final phrase. By demanding step-by-step reasoning, you&amp;rsquo;re not just getting a more accurate answer - you&amp;rsquo;re getting insight into the problem-solving process itself. This approach renders the old way of asking math questions obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My perspective on this was permanently altered after watching it solve a logistics problem that had stumped our team for weeks. The AI didn&amp;rsquo;t just give us the right answer; it showed us three different approaches we hadn&amp;rsquo;t considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prompt-chaining-building-workflows-that-scale&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#prompt-chaining-building-workflows-that-scale&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Prompt Chaining: Building Workflows That Scale
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is where the theoretical meets the practical. Single prompts have their limits, but chaining creates something more powerful - a structured workflow where each response becomes the foundation for the next question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essential insight to grasp is that complex projects aren&amp;rsquo;t just big questions. They&amp;rsquo;re sequences of smaller, focused questions where context builds progressively. Instead of asking for a complete marketing strategy, you architect a process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First prompt: &amp;ldquo;Brainstorm five marketing angles for a new eco-friendly coffee cup.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second prompt: &amp;ldquo;Great. Using angle #2, &amp;lsquo;Style That Sustains,&amp;rsquo; write three distinct Instagram post concepts, including captions and visuals.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each step is digestible, focused, and feeds naturally into the next. This approach overturns the conventional wisdom about how we should structure our requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;structured-output-data-ready-for-action&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#structured-output-data-ready-for-action&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Structured Output: Data Ready for Action
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let my trial and error be your shortcut here. The most frustrating part of early AI work wasn&amp;rsquo;t getting bad answers - it was getting good answers in unusable formats. You&amp;rsquo;d spend as much time reformatting the response as you did crafting the original prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution is deceptively simple: explicitly specify the output format you need. JSON for data processing, Markdown tables for documentation, XML for system integration. The AI can handle these formats natively, but only if you ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Compare the top three flagship smartphones. Present the info in a Markdown table with columns for: Model, Key Features, and Starting Price.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To distill it down to its core: structured output transforms AI responses from interesting reads into actionable data. It&amp;rsquo;s the difference between getting information and getting results you can immediately use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-committee-of-experts-simulating-real-debate&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-committee-of-experts-simulating-real-debate&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Committee of Experts: Simulating Real Debate
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if we&amp;rsquo;ve been looking at AI perspective all wrong? Instead of treating it as a single voice, you can orchestrate multiple viewpoints within a single conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee approach forces the AI to inhabit different roles and present conflicting perspectives. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just creative writing - it&amp;rsquo;s a systematic way to uncover blind spots and explore the full spectrum of an issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Analyze the impact of a 4-day work week by simulating a brief discussion between a CEO, an economist, and an employee wellness expert. Summarize each one&amp;rsquo;s main point.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technique will completely reshape how you approach complex analysis. Instead of getting one perspective (which might be biased toward the AI&amp;rsquo;s training data), you get a structured debate that reveals tensions and trade-offs you might not have considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;self-critique-the-internal-feedback-loop&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#self-critique-the-internal-feedback-loop&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Self-Critique: The Internal Feedback Loop
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This realization introduces a new layer of sophistication to AI interaction. You can turn the AI into its own editor, creating a feedback loop that improves output quality without requiring multiple different tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process is elegantly simple: generate, critique, revise. First, get an initial response. Then ask the AI to evaluate its own work against specific criteria - tone, clarity, persuasiveness, accuracy. Finally, have it rewrite based on its own critique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First prompt: &amp;ldquo;Write a short, unenthusiastic business email asking a client for a testimonial.&amp;rdquo;
Follow-up: &amp;ldquo;Now, critique that email for being too passive and uninspiring. Then, rewrite it to be more persuasive and cheerful.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scars from early encounters with generic AI output taught me to never settle for the first draft. Self-critique transforms AI from a one-shot tool into a collaborative partner that can iterate and improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;templated-prompting-consistency-at-scale&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#templated-prompting-consistency-at-scale&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Templated Prompting: Consistency at Scale
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;After wrestling with recurring tasks across multiple projects, it became clear that efficiency demanded systematization. Templated prompting creates reusable frameworks that ensure consistency while maintaining quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core principle is straightforward: create detailed templates with placeholders, then fill them with specific data for each use case. This is particularly powerful for weekly reports, client communications, or content creation where structure matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Use my weekly report template. Subject: Project Update: [Project Name]. Body: Accomplishments: [List of accomplishments]. Challenges: [List of challenges]. Next Steps: [List of next steps]. Now, fill it out with the following details&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach renders ad-hoc prompting obsolete for repetitive tasks. You&amp;rsquo;re not just saving time; you&amp;rsquo;re ensuring that your communication maintains a consistent professional standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;iterative-refinement-the-art-of-the-follow-up&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#iterative-refinement-the-art-of-the-follow-up&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Iterative Refinement: The Art of the Follow-Up
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ultimate takeaway from years of AI interaction is this: perfection is a conversation, not a command. The most valuable results come from treating AI interaction as an iterative process rather than a single exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start broad, then narrow. Get an initial response, analyze what works and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t, then provide specific feedback for improvement. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just about getting better answers - it&amp;rsquo;s about training yourself to think more precisely about what you actually want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial: &amp;ldquo;Write an intro for a blog post about productivity.&amp;rdquo;
Refinement: &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s a bit bland. Can you rewrite it to be more dynamic? Start with a relatable scenario about the &amp;lsquo;Sunday Scaries&amp;rsquo; and use a more motivational tone.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t just theory; this is from the front lines of practical AI work. The willingness to iterate separates good results from genuinely valuable ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-new-paradigm&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-new-paradigm&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The New Paradigm
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, where do we go from here? These techniques aren&amp;rsquo;t just improvements to your AI toolkit - they represent a complete reconceptualization of human-AI collaboration. You&amp;rsquo;re no longer a user asking questions; you&amp;rsquo;re an architect designing thought processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation doesn&amp;rsquo;t end here; the real test is applying these frameworks to your own work. Each technique becomes more powerful when combined with others, creating sophisticated workflows that would be impossible with traditional tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope is that this provides a new lens for understanding what&amp;rsquo;s possible when you move beyond simple prompting to intentional AI architecture. The tools are ready. The question is whether you&amp;rsquo;re ready to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Real Problem with AI Today? Nobody Knows What Works Tomorrow</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/stability/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/stability/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://192.168.100.63:1313/img/tintinconfused.png" alt="Featured image of post The Real Problem with AI Today? Nobody Knows What Works Tomorrow" /&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-real-problem-with-ai-today-nobody-knows-what-works-tomorrow&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-real-problem-with-ai-today-nobody-knows-what-works-tomorrow&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Real Problem with AI Today? Nobody Knows What Works Tomorrow
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been living in AI tools for the past year. Multiple subscriptions, endless experiments, daily workflows built around these systems. And I&amp;rsquo;m starting to think we&amp;rsquo;re all participating in the world&amp;rsquo;s most expensive beta test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how my mornings go: Yesterday&amp;rsquo;s perfectly functioning ChatGPT woke up stupid. The code that was flowing like water twelve hours ago now reads like it was written by someone who just discovered what a semicolon is. So I jump to Claude – except artifacts decided to take a vacation. Fine, Gemini it is. Works brilliantly. For exactly one day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we reset the whole circus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-great-instability-crisis&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-great-instability-crisis&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Great Instability Crisis
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Browse any AI community and you&amp;rsquo;ll witness a fascinating phenomenon. Half the posts are people convinced their AI tool had a lobotomy overnight. The other half are discovering that some random update made their previously useless tool suddenly brilliant. It&amp;rsquo;s technological whiplash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explanations we get are beautifully meaningless. &amp;ldquo;Backend optimizations.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Model improvements.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Training updates.&amp;rdquo; Might as well say &amp;ldquo;we changed some stuff&amp;rdquo; and call it a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what kills me – I&amp;rsquo;m paying premium prices for tools that fundamentally change their behavior without warning. Imagine if Microsoft Word randomly decided that today it only writes in iambic pentameter. That&amp;rsquo;s the level of consistency we&amp;rsquo;re dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;racing-toward-mediocrity&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#racing-toward-mediocrity&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Racing Toward Mediocrity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The competition between AI companies has created this bizarre dynamic where everyone&amp;rsquo;s sprinting to release features that barely work. OpenAI sees Claude&amp;rsquo;s artifacts and panics. Google watches GitHub Copilot and scrambles. Everyone&amp;rsquo;s so busy keeping up with everyone else that nobody&amp;rsquo;s actually finishing anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s coding assistant launch? It had all the polish of a middle school science project. But hey, Claude had one, so out it goes. Ship now, fix later – except &amp;ldquo;later&amp;rdquo; never really arrives because there&amp;rsquo;s always another half-baked feature to rush out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-stability-manifesto&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-stability-manifesto&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Stability Manifesto
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me paint you a picture of what we actually need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version Dichotomy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Linux world figured this out decades ago. You want cutting-edge chaos? Here&amp;rsquo;s your rolling release. You want to actually get work done? Here&amp;rsquo;s Debian Stable, unchanged since the dawn of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give me ChatGPT-Stable that updates quarterly with actual testing. Let the adrenaline junkies play with ChatGPT-Edge where every refresh is a new adventure. I&amp;rsquo;ll take boring reliability over exciting uncertainty every single time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose-Built Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This obsession with omni-models needs to die. I don&amp;rsquo;t need my code assistant to write poetry. I don&amp;rsquo;t need my creative writing tool to debug Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropic almost gets this with their Opus/Sonnet/Haiku split, but even they&amp;rsquo;re muddying the waters. OpenAI? Their model naming looks like someone got drunk with a label maker. GPT-4, o1, o3 (apparently o2 was too mainstream), various &amp;ldquo;turbo&amp;rdquo; versions that may or may not exist anymore, and enough &amp;ldquo;mini&amp;rdquo; variants to stock a convenience store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick. A. Lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Naming That Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Require a Decoder Ring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I challenge anyone to explain OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s naming convention without sounding like they&amp;rsquo;re reading from a random number generator. We&amp;rsquo;ve transcended confusion and entered the realm of performance art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-productivity-paradox&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-productivity-paradox&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Productivity Paradox
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every workflow disruption costs me 20-30 minutes minimum. Not just the switching – the testing, the adapting to different interfaces, the rewriting prompts that worked yesterday but fail today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scale that across millions of users. We&amp;rsquo;re hemorrhaging productivity in the name of progress. The tools designed to make us more efficient are becoming the biggest efficiency drains in our workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve started keeping a spreadsheet of which model works best for which task on which day. That&amp;rsquo;s insane. I&amp;rsquo;m doing data analysis just to figure out which AI can do data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-alternative-universe&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#an-alternative-universe&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;An Alternative Universe
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Picture this: You wake up knowing exactly how your AI tools will behave. Your carefully crafted prompts work the same way they did yesterday. The model that excels at code generation still excels at code generation. Revolutionary concept, I know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some radical proposals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stability Contracts&lt;/strong&gt;: Guarantee model behavior for minimum 90-day periods. Not &amp;ldquo;mostly the same with minor tweaks.&amp;rdquo; Identical. Frozen. Immutable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-World Beta Testing&lt;/strong&gt;: Stop testing on production. Those &amp;ldquo;minor updates&amp;rdquo; that break everything? Maybe catch those before inflicting them on paying customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparent Change Logs&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;We reduced latency by 50ms but code generation accuracy dropped 3% in recursive functions&amp;rdquo; beats &amp;ldquo;performance improvements&amp;rdquo; every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feature Moratorium&lt;/strong&gt;: Declare a six-month freeze on new features. Fix what exists. Make it bulletproof. Then, and only then, add the next shiny thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-excellence-of-mundane-consistency&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-excellence-of-mundane-consistency&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Excellence of Mundane Consistency
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve confused innovation with instability. The most innovative thing any AI company could do right now is&amp;hellip; nothing. Stop touching things. Let them work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t need my AI assistant to be marginally smarter next week if it means it might be catastrophically dumber instead. I need it to be boringly, predictably, reliably competent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market leader won&amp;rsquo;t be whoever scores 0.5% higher on some benchmark nobody understands. It&amp;rsquo;ll be whoever first realizes that professionals need professional tools – tools that show up ready to work every single day, not tools that require a morning diagnostic to determine today&amp;rsquo;s personality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-reckoning&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-reckoning&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Reckoning
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the truth these companies need to hear: Your users aren&amp;rsquo;t beta testers. We&amp;rsquo;re not excited by surprise feature drops that break our workflows. We&amp;rsquo;re not impressed by rush-released features that sort of work sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AI revolution promised to augment human capability. Instead, we&amp;rsquo;re spending our augmented capability figuring out why our augmentation tools stopped working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s my challenge to the AI giants: Be brave enough to be boring. Be innovative enough to be stable. Be competitive by being consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because right now, the most disruptive thing in AI would be reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are you thriving in this chaos, or are you also maintaining spreadsheets to track which AI is having a good day?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
