<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>AGI on The Patch Panel</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/agi/</link>
        <description>Recent content in AGI on The Patch Panel</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 10:45:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/agi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>AGI: The Dumb Smart Thing That Might Change Everything</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/agi/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 10:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/agi/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://192.168.100.63:1313/img/head/agi.png" alt="Featured image of post AGI: The Dumb Smart Thing That Might Change Everything" /&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ai-summary&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#ai-summary&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI Summary
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve evolved from statistical ML to GenAI, but AGI requires a fundamentally different breakthrough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Current GenAI has a ceiling - better prompting and more parameters won&amp;rsquo;t get us to general intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;ldquo;humans out of the loop&amp;rdquo; narrative fails because today&amp;rsquo;s AI lacks true understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus should shift from AGI timeline speculation to maximizing what current AI can actually do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-evolution-we-keep-misunderstanding&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-evolution-we-keep-misunderstanding&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Evolution We Keep Misunderstanding
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every few weeks, another breathless announcement proclaims we&amp;rsquo;re on the verge of artificial general intelligence. Another benchmark falls. Another demo looks uncannily human. The investment dollars flow like water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s the thing: we&amp;rsquo;re conflating progress in GenAI with progress toward AGI. They&amp;rsquo;re not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand why AGI isn&amp;rsquo;t as close as the hype suggests, we need to be clear about what we&amp;rsquo;re actually talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-statistics-to-synthesis-the-ai-journey-so-far&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#from-statistics-to-synthesis-the-ai-journey-so-far&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;From Statistics to Synthesis: The AI Journey So Far
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Traditional AI/ML (Pre-2020s)&lt;/strong&gt;: This was the world of random forests, SVMs, and neural networks doing specific tasks. Image classification. Fraud detection. Recommendation engines. Statistical learning at its finest - powerful but narrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GenAI Revolution (2020-Present)&lt;/strong&gt;: The transformer breakthrough gave us something new - models that could generate plausible text, code, and images. ChatGPT, Claude, Midjourney. These feel magical because they&amp;rsquo;re creative in ways traditional ML never was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AGI (The Promised Land)&lt;/strong&gt;: A system that can understand, learn, and apply knowledge across any domain, just like humans. Not pattern matching - actual reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jump from GenAI to AGI isn&amp;rsquo;t iterative. It&amp;rsquo;s a completely different class of problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-genai-has-a-ceiling&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-genai-has-a-ceiling&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why GenAI Has a Ceiling
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current GenAI is remarkable at synthesis and pattern matching. It can write poetry, debug code, and explain quantum physics. But it&amp;rsquo;s fundamentally doing sophisticated autocomplete based on training data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The limitations become obvious when you push:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask for reasoning about truly novel situations - you get confident-sounding hallucinations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Request multi-step logical deduction - it falls apart beyond simple chains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probe for genuine understanding - you find elaborate pattern matching, not comprehension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren&amp;rsquo;t bugs to be fixed with GPT-5 or Claude 4. They&amp;rsquo;re fundamental to how these systems work. You can&amp;rsquo;t get from &amp;ldquo;predicting likely token sequences&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;understanding meaning&amp;rdquo; just by scaling up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-humans-out-of-the-loop-delusion&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-humans-out-of-the-loop-delusion&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Humans Out of the Loop&amp;rdquo; Delusion
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GenAI hype machine loves to promise autonomous systems that will replace human judgment. But watch what happens when people actually try this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI-generated code that &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; correct but contains subtle logic errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer service bots that infuriate users with plausible-sounding non-answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content that passes a surface read but crumbles under expert scrutiny&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Products degrade rapidly when humans step back too far from current AI systems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t because the AI needs more training. It&amp;rsquo;s because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually understand what it&amp;rsquo;s doing. GenAI excels at mimicry, not comprehension. And mimicry without understanding is a recipe for gradual system failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-breakthrough-were-waiting-for&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-breakthrough-were-waiting-for&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Breakthrough We&amp;rsquo;re Waiting For
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting to AGI isn&amp;rsquo;t about making transformers bigger or training on more data. We need something fundamentally new - a different approach to machine intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What might that look like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems that build actual world models, not just statistical associations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Architectures that can reason causally, not just correlatively&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approaches that understand symbols and meaning, not just patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody knows what this breakthrough will be. That&amp;rsquo;s precisely why timeline predictions are meaningless. You can&amp;rsquo;t schedule a paradigm shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chinas-speed-advantage-in-the-wrong-race&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#chinas-speed-advantage-in-the-wrong-race&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;China&amp;rsquo;s Speed Advantage in the Wrong Race
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, China can ignore copyright and train on anything. Yes, they have unlimited government funding. Yes, they can deploy without Western regulatory constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they&amp;rsquo;re optimizing for the current paradigm - building better GenAI faster. If AGI requires a fundamental breakthrough rather than incremental improvement, their advantages become less relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t regulate your way to AGI, but you also can&amp;rsquo;t deregulate your way there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next Einstein moment in AI research could come from anywhere. A small lab. A university researcher. Someone thinking orthogonally to the current approach. Throwing more resources at the wrong approach just gets you there faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-current-ai-actually-tells-us&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-current-ai-actually-tells-us&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Current AI Actually Tells Us
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GenAI revolution has taught us invaluable lessons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scale alone isn&amp;rsquo;t enough&lt;/strong&gt; - We&amp;rsquo;ve hit diminishing returns on &amp;ldquo;just make it bigger&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emergence is limited&lt;/strong&gt; - New capabilities appear, but fundamental understanding doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration is harder than innovation&lt;/strong&gt; - Getting AI to work reliably in the real world remains brutally difficult&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These lessons matter because they show us what AGI &lt;em&gt;won&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; be: it won&amp;rsquo;t be ChatGPT-7 with more parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-questions-we-should-actually-be-asking&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-questions-we-should-actually-be-asking&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Questions We Should Actually Be Asking
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of &amp;ldquo;When will AGI arrive?&amp;rdquo;, consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we maximize value from current GenAI without overpromising?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What fundamental research areas have we neglected while chasing scale?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we prepare for a breakthrough we can&amp;rsquo;t predict?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens to the AI investment bubble when people realize current approaches have limits?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren&amp;rsquo;t as sexy as AGI predictions, but they&amp;rsquo;re grounded in reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-im-still-fascinated&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-im-still-fascinated&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why I&amp;rsquo;m Still Fascinated
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite my skepticism about near-term AGI, I remain deeply engaged with AI development. The technical challenges are genuinely interesting. The potential impact - whenever it arrives - is profound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my optimism is tempered by pragmatism. We&amp;rsquo;re not one clever training run away from general intelligence. We&amp;rsquo;re waiting for a breakthrough that might come tomorrow or might take decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That uncertainty is both frustrating and exciting. It means we can&amp;rsquo;t coast on current approaches. We have to keep exploring, keep questioning, keep pushing boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bottom-line&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-bottom-line&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Bottom Line
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where we are&lt;/strong&gt;: Powerful GenAI with fundamental limitations&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Where AGI is&lt;/strong&gt;: Waiting for a breakthrough we can&amp;rsquo;t schedule&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What we should do&lt;/strong&gt;: Build amazing things with current AI while staying realistic about its limits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GenAI revolution has given us incredible tools. But it&amp;rsquo;s also shown us how far we are from true artificial general intelligence. That gap isn&amp;rsquo;t closing as fast as the hype suggests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s for the best. We&amp;rsquo;re still figuring out how to handle narrow AI responsibly. Perhaps we need this time to prepare for something that will genuinely change everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AGI will arrive eventually. But probably not through the path we&amp;rsquo;re currently racing down. When the breakthrough comes, it&amp;rsquo;ll likely surprise us all - including those claiming to know when it&amp;rsquo;s coming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then, let&amp;rsquo;s build useful things with the remarkable tools we have, while staying honest about what they can&amp;rsquo;t do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
