<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Team Management on My Blog</title>
    <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/categories/team-management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Team Management on My Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 03:00:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/categories/team-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why &#39;The Smartest Person in the Room&#39; is Killing Your Data Science Team</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/genius/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 03:00:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/genius/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why &amp;lsquo;The Smartest Person in the Room&amp;rsquo; is Killing Your Data Science Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every data science leader has met them—the brilliant individual who can solve problems no one else can crack, who knows the codebase inside out, who seems to have every algorithm memorized, and who can debug the most complex models in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re the hero, the go-to person, the one who pulls off miracles when deadlines loom. They&amp;rsquo;re the smartest person in the room.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Scale a Data Science Team Without Losing Agility</title>
      <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/agility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/agility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-to-scale-a-data-science-team-without-losing-agility&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Scale a Data Science Team Without Losing Agility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched dozens of data science teams follow the same painful trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They start small—three or four talented individuals moving fast, shipping models, and delivering insights that make the business take notice. Leadership gets excited. Budgets expand. Headcount doubles, then doubles again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And then, somehow, everything grinds to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The team that once deployed models in weeks now takes months. Projects that used to flow seamlessly now get bogged down in meetings and documentation. The scrappy, high-impact group has transformed into a sluggish bureaucracy that spends more time managing processes than delivering value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
