<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>AIG on My Blog</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/aig/</link>
        <description>Recent content in AIG on My Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/aig/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>AIG: The Dumb Smart Thing That Might Change Everything</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/agi/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/musings/agi/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;agi-is-coming-and-im-not-sure-how-i-feel-about-it&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#agi-is-coming-and-im-not-sure-how-i-feel-about-it&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AGI is Coming and I&amp;rsquo;m Not Sure How I Feel About It
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why the &amp;ldquo;thinking machine&amp;rdquo; might arrive sooner than we&amp;rsquo;re ready for&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every few weeks, there&amp;rsquo;s another AI breakthrough that gets everyone excited about artificial general intelligence - you know, the sci-fi dream of machines that can actually think like humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been following this stuff closely, and honestly? I&amp;rsquo;m torn between fascination and low-key dread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential is incredible. But we&amp;rsquo;re also racing toward something we might not be able to control, and that&amp;rsquo;s&amp;hellip; unsettling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-agi-feels-inevitable-now&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-agi-feels-inevitable-now&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why AGI Feels Inevitable Now
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I used to think AGI was decades away. That&amp;rsquo;s changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The momentum is undeniable. Every major tech company is throwing billions at this problem. The smartest people on the planet are working on it. And the breakthroughs keep coming faster than anyone expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve gone from &amp;ldquo;AI that recognizes cats in photos&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;AI that writes code and passes bar exams&amp;rdquo; in just a few years. The jump from &amp;ldquo;really good pattern matching&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;actual thinking&amp;rdquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel that far anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The question isn&amp;rsquo;t if we&amp;rsquo;ll create AGI. It&amp;rsquo;s when.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s where things get interesting (and terrifying).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-job-question-everyones-asking&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-job-question-everyones-asking&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Job Question Everyone&amp;rsquo;s Asking
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Will AI take my job?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depends what you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in creative or analytical work:&lt;/strong&gt; Probably safe for now. AGI might change how you work, but it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely to replace you entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in routine knowledge work:&lt;/strong&gt; Bookkeeping, basic legal research, customer support, data entry&amp;hellip; yeah, you should probably be thinking about what&amp;rsquo;s next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The efficiency gains are too tempting. When a company can automate entire departments overnight, they will. That&amp;rsquo;s just business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when Universal Basic Income stops being a Silicon Valley fantasy and becomes a real policy discussion. What happens to society when AI can do most of the jobs that currently support the middle class?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re about to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;chinas-unfair-advantage&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#chinas-unfair-advantage&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;China&amp;rsquo;s Unfair Advantage
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s something that doesn&amp;rsquo;t get enough attention: China has a massive head start in the AGI race, and it&amp;rsquo;s not just because of their tech prowess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They can move faster because they ignore rules everyone else follows.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copyright laws? Irrelevant. They can scrape and train on anything without worrying about lawsuits. Meanwhile, Western companies spend months navigating legal challenges just to use training data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Government backing changes everything.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While American AI companies worry about venture funding and quarterly profits, China&amp;rsquo;s government is writing blank checks for AGI research. No short-term pressure, unlimited resources, single-minded focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects like China&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Manus&amp;rdquo; AGI system are reportedly getting closer to true general intelligence than anything in the West. If that&amp;rsquo;s true, we might be in for a surprise about who reaches AGI first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. and Europe need to decide: adapt their approach or accept second place in the most important technological race of our lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ethics-problem-no-one-wants-to-talk-about&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-ethics-problem-no-one-wants-to-talk-about&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Ethics Problem No One Wants to Talk About
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone agrees AGI should be developed &amp;ldquo;ethically.&amp;rdquo; But what does that actually mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Should AGI serve humanity or be independent?&lt;/strong&gt;
If we create something truly intelligent, does it deserve rights? Or is it just a very sophisticated tool?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who decides what AGI can do?&lt;/strong&gt;
When an artificial mind can make decisions that affect millions of people, who&amp;rsquo;s responsible for those choices?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about bias and control?&lt;/strong&gt;
Current AI systems already show troubling biases. Now imagine those biases embedded in something with general intelligence and real-world power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The scariest question: What if we lose control?&lt;/strong&gt;
What happens when we create something smarter than us that doesn&amp;rsquo;t share our values or priorities?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have answers to these questions. Neither does anyone else. But we&amp;rsquo;re racing ahead anyway, which feels&amp;hellip; reckless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-im-not-panicking-yet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-im-not-panicking-yet&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why I&amp;rsquo;m Not Panicking (Yet)
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite all this uncertainty, I still love working with AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current AI is powerful and useful, but it&amp;rsquo;s also reassuringly limited. ChatGPT can write code and answer questions, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually understand what it&amp;rsquo;s doing. It&amp;rsquo;s pattern matching at an incredible scale, but it&amp;rsquo;s not thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s AI is like a really smart parrot&lt;/strong&gt; - it can repeat back information in impressive ways, but there&amp;rsquo;s no real comprehension behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s what keeps me from losing sleep. As long as AI remains sophisticated autocomplete rather than actual intelligence, we&amp;rsquo;re still in control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when that changes - when AI stops predicting the next word and starts genuinely understanding - everything changes with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-uncomfortable-timeline&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-uncomfortable-timeline&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Uncomfortable Timeline
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where we are now:&lt;/strong&gt; AI that&amp;rsquo;s impressive but fundamentally limited&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where we&amp;rsquo;re heading:&lt;/strong&gt; AI that can actually think, plan, and act independently&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The gap between these:&lt;/strong&gt; Probably smaller than most people realize&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happens in that gap:&lt;/strong&gt; We figure out how to handle the most transformative technology in human history&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No pressure, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-keeps-me-up-at-night&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-keeps-me-up-at-night&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Keeps Me Up at Night
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not the technology itself - it&amp;rsquo;s the speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re moving incredibly fast toward something we don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand, with rules we haven&amp;rsquo;t written, guided by economic incentives that don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily align with human welfare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The optimistic scenario:&lt;/strong&gt; AGI helps solve climate change, cure diseases, and ushers in an era of unprecedented prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The pessimistic scenario:&lt;/strong&gt; We create something we can&amp;rsquo;t control that fundamentally changes what it means to be human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The realistic scenario:&lt;/strong&gt; Probably somewhere in between, but with a lot more disruption than anyone&amp;rsquo;s prepared for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bottom-line&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#bottom-line&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Bottom Line
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;AGI is coming whether we&amp;rsquo;re ready or not. The technical hurdles are being cleared faster than expected. The economic incentives are too strong to ignore. The geopolitical competition is too intense to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What we need:&lt;/strong&gt; Serious conversations about ethics, control, and consequences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What we&amp;rsquo;re getting:&lt;/strong&gt; A race to build the most powerful AI as quickly as possible&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The gap between these:&lt;/strong&gt; That&amp;rsquo;s what worries me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still fascinated by AI and excited about its potential. But I&amp;rsquo;m also increasingly aware that we&amp;rsquo;re approaching a point of no return - a moment when AI stops being a tool and becomes something else entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And once we cross that line, there&amp;rsquo;s no going back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The future is being written by AI researchers in labs around the world. Let&amp;rsquo;s hope they&amp;rsquo;re thinking about more than just the next breakthrough.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
