<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Communication on My Blog</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/communication/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Communication on My Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:44:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.100.63:1313/tags/communication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>What Business Leaders Get Wrong About Data Science (And How to Educate Them)</title>
        <link>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/leaders/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 02:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://192.168.100.63:1313/datascience/leaders/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;your-executives-think-data-science-is-magic-and-its-killing-your-projects&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#your-executives-think-data-science-is-magic-and-its-killing-your-projects&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Your Executives Think Data Science is Magic (And It&amp;rsquo;s Killing Your Projects)
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to educate leadership without crushing their dreams&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Can&amp;rsquo;t we just use AI to predict which customers will leave us?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve heard this exact question in probably 50 different boardrooms. The executive asking is genuinely excited about the possibilities, completely sincere about wanting to use data better, and absolutely clueless about what they&amp;rsquo;re actually asking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enthusiasm is fantastic. The expectations? Total fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a decade of watching brilliant data science teams crash into unrealistic business expectations, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that the biggest obstacle to successful data projects isn&amp;rsquo;t technical complexity - it&amp;rsquo;s the gap between what executives think data science can do and what it actually does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the uncomfortable truth: most business leaders think data science is magic. And until we fix that, we&amp;rsquo;ll keep building amazing solutions that nobody uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-top-5-fantasies-business-leaders-have-about-data-science&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-top-5-fantasies-business-leaders-have-about-data-science&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Top 5 Fantasies Business Leaders Have About Data Science
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;fantasy-1-its-all-about-cool-ai-algorithms&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fantasy-1-its-all-about-cool-ai-algorithms&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Fantasy #1: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s All About Cool AI Algorithms&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What they think:&lt;/strong&gt; Data scientists spend their days building sophisticated AI models that solve business problems automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The reality:&lt;/strong&gt; 80% of data science is cleaning messy data, and 20% is actual modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched one healthcare company spend $2M on an &amp;ldquo;AI initiative&amp;rdquo; before realizing their patient data was scattered across 15 different systems with inconsistent formats. They would have been way better off spending that first million on basic data integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why this matters:&lt;/strong&gt; When executives focus on algorithms instead of data infrastructure, they set impossible timelines and get frustrated when teams spend months on &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo; data work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fantasy-2-more-data--better-results&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fantasy-2-more-data--better-results&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Fantasy #2: &amp;ldquo;More Data = Better Results&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What they think:&lt;/strong&gt; The path to insights is collecting every possible piece of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The reality:&lt;/strong&gt; Most companies are drowning in irrelevant information while missing the data they actually need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One retail client was storing 200+ variables per customer but only using 12 for actual decisions. The storage costs for unused data? Over $500K annually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why this matters:&lt;/strong&gt; Data hoarding creates expensive storage costs, analysis paralysis, and security risks without delivering any value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fantasy-3-well-see-roi-immediately&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fantasy-3-well-see-roi-immediately&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Fantasy #3: &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;ll See ROI Immediately&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What they think:&lt;/strong&gt; Data science projects should deliver clear returns within a quarter, like buying new software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The reality:&lt;/strong&gt; Data science is more like R&amp;amp;D than IT implementation. The best projects often require experimentation and iteration before showing value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We built a customer lifetime value model for a subscription business that took three quarters to show impact. But that impact was worth $14M annually. The executives almost killed the project at month two because they weren&amp;rsquo;t seeing immediate results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fantasy-4-any-good-data-scientist-can-solve-any-problem&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fantasy-4-any-good-data-scientist-can-solve-any-problem&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Fantasy #4: &amp;ldquo;Any Good Data Scientist Can Solve Any Problem&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What they think:&lt;/strong&gt; Data scientists are universal problem solvers who can tackle anything with enough data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The reality:&lt;/strong&gt; Data science is incredibly specialized. A recommendation system expert might struggle with time series forecasting. A statistics wizard might know nothing about deep learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we restructured one client&amp;rsquo;s team around domains of expertise instead of treating everyone as interchangeable, project success rates jumped from 35% to over 70%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fantasy-5-data-science-gives-us-the-answer&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fantasy-5-data-science-gives-us-the-answer&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Fantasy #5: &amp;ldquo;Data Science Gives Us The Answer&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What they think:&lt;/strong&gt; Models will tell us exactly what will happen and exactly what to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The reality:&lt;/strong&gt; Data science deals in probabilities, not certainties. A model might say a customer has a 70% chance of churning - it can&amp;rsquo;t guarantee they will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One financial services client initially rejected our loan default model because it couldn&amp;rsquo;t predict with certainty which loans would fail. They were missing the point that improving probability estimates by even 10% was worth millions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-wake-them-up-without-crushing-their-dreams&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#how-to-wake-them-up-without-crushing-their-dreams&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How to Wake Them Up (Without Crushing Their Dreams)
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;speak-business-not-technical&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#speak-business-not-technical&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Speak Business, Not Technical
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t say:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;We improved model accuracy by 12%&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Say:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;We reduced customer acquisition costs by $50 per customer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t say:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;We need to address data quality issues&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Say:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Poor data is costing us 3 months on every project&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started translating everything into business outcomes, and suddenly executive engagement in our reviews went from 20% to 80%. They weren&amp;rsquo;t less interested before - they just couldn&amp;rsquo;t connect our work to things they cared about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;show-them-dont-tell-them&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#show-them-dont-tell-them&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Show Them, Don&amp;rsquo;t Tell Them
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abstract explanations don&amp;rsquo;t change minds. Real experiences do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try this:&lt;/strong&gt; Run a &amp;ldquo;Data Science Reality&amp;rdquo; workshop where executives manually clean a small dataset, then try to draw conclusions. The frustration they experience firsthand teaches them more than any presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Or this:&lt;/strong&gt; Create an interactive demo showing how changing data quality affects business outcomes. Let them see what happens when you feed good vs. bad data into the same model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;start-small-and-win-big&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#start-small-and-win-big&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Start Small and Win Big
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to correct every misconception at once, pick quick wins that prove your point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one retail executive insisted AI could optimize their entire pricing strategy overnight, we proposed a pilot on one product category instead. We delivered a 4% margin improvement in eight weeks. That small win earned us the credibility to have realistic conversations about what a full system would actually require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;make-them-part-of-the-process&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#make-them-part-of-the-process&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Make Them Part of the Process
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business leaders who participate in data science projects develop way more realistic expectations than those who just get the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a steering committee&lt;/strong&gt; with business representation&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Involve executives in problem definition&lt;/strong&gt; and feature selection&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Hold regular open houses&lt;/strong&gt; where they can see work in progress&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Implement &amp;ldquo;ride-along&amp;rdquo; programs&lt;/strong&gt; where they spend a day with the data team&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we started a steering committee at one company, project completion rates increased 60%. Not because our data science got better, but because business leaders understood what was actually possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;make-the-hidden-costs-visible&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#make-the-hidden-costs-visible&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Make the Hidden Costs Visible
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business leaders undervalue data preparation because they don&amp;rsquo;t see its cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track and report time spent&lt;/strong&gt; on data prep vs. modeling&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Quantify the cost of poor data quality&lt;/strong&gt; in delayed projects and missed opportunities&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Create &amp;ldquo;data readiness assessments&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; before starting projects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed a &amp;ldquo;data readiness index&amp;rdquo; that scored potential projects 1-100 based on data availability and quality. Projects scoring below 60 had to include a separate data preparation phase with its own timeline and budget. This simple tool reduced project failures by 40%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-90-day-executive-education-program&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-90-day-executive-education-program&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The 90-Day Executive Education Program
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re serious about fixing the expectations problem, you need a structured approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;month-1-reality-check&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#month-1-reality-check&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Month 1: Reality Check
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Survey executives to identify specific misconceptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a &amp;ldquo;data science reality&amp;rdquo; guide for your organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document the full process of one successful project - including all the messy parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify 2-3 quick win opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;month-2-experience-building&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#month-2-experience-building&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Month 2: Experience Building
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the &amp;ldquo;Data Science Reality&amp;rdquo; workshop for leadership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start the steering committee with monthly meetings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch at least one quick win project with heavy executive involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a dashboard showing how data scientists actually spend their time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;month-3-new-systems&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#month-3-new-systems&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Month 3: New Systems
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share results from quick wins, emphasizing process as much as outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement data readiness requirements for new projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create an executive resource center with case studies and guides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish quarterly reviews that address expectations vs. reality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-success-actually-looks-like&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-success-actually-looks-like&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Success Actually Looks Like
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;before-education&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#before-education&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Before Education
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;What does the data science team actually do all day?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Projects get killed when they don&amp;rsquo;t show immediate results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unrealistic timelines based on algorithm complexity, not data reality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frustration when &amp;ldquo;AI&amp;rdquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t solve every problem instantly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-education&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#after-education&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;After Education
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executives fighting for data science resources because they understand the value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic project timelines that account for data preparation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investment in data infrastructure alongside analytics capabilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patience for experimentation and iteration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-goal-realistic-data-optimism&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-goal-realistic-data-optimism&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Goal: Realistic Data Optimism
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The point isn&amp;rsquo;t to crush executive enthusiasm for data science. It&amp;rsquo;s to channel that enthusiasm in productive directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The best organizations maintain &amp;ldquo;realistic data optimism&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; - genuine excitement about data science potential combined with clear-eyed understanding of what it takes to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They know that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data science is a process, not a product&lt;/strong&gt; requiring ongoing investment and patience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data quality matters as much as analytical sophistication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not every problem needs advanced AI&lt;/strong&gt; - sometimes simple analytics deliver more value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data scientists are partners, not magicians&lt;/strong&gt; who need context and reasonable expectations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-real-competitive-advantage&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-real-competitive-advantage&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Real Competitive Advantage
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Companies that get the most value from data science aren&amp;rsquo;t necessarily those with the biggest teams or fanciest technology. They&amp;rsquo;re the ones where business and data leaders share a realistic understanding of what&amp;rsquo;s possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the biggest advantage isn&amp;rsquo;t having better algorithms than everyone else - it&amp;rsquo;s having better alignment between your data capabilities and your business strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bottom-line&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-bottom-line&#34; class=&#34;header-anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Bottom Line
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your executives&amp;rsquo; enthusiasm for data science is an asset, not a problem. But enthusiasm without understanding leads to failed projects, wasted money, and frustrated teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution isn&amp;rsquo;t to lower expectations - it&amp;rsquo;s to educate leadership about what realistic success looks like. When business leaders understand both the potential and the process of data science, magic happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not the fantasy magic they initially imagined, but something better: sustainable, scalable business impact driven by data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s worth way more than any algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most successful data science organizations aren&amp;rsquo;t those with the most advanced technology - they&amp;rsquo;re those with the best communication between business and technical teams. Start there.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
